VIGNESH SELVARAJ

P: (289)-981-0562 | E: vigneshse@gmail.com | L: Toronto, Canada

LI: www.linkedin.com/in/vigneshse | GH: https://github.com/vigneshse

SUMMARY

Software Development Engineer - experience in design, development, and implementation of scalable and distributed applications over 12 years. My specialization is Back-end engineering – gRPC & REST APIs, Microservices & Cloud-Native architecture, Java, Kotlin, Python, Spring-boot, AWS & GCP, SOLID & OOD Design Patterns, Test Driven Development and Agile Methodology includes Scrum and Kanban.

SKILLS & INTERESTS

Java • Kotlin • Python • Spring-boot • gRPC • REST APIs • Microservices • Data Structures & Algorithms • AWS • GCP

EDUCATION

VIT UNIVERSITY - VELLORE INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY | Vellore, INDIA

May 2008

Bachelor of Technology, Computer Science Engineering (3.2 GPA)

Honors & Activities: Class Representative (Class size: 60), Students Association

THIAGARAJAR POLYTECHNIC COLLEGE | Salem, INDIA

Apr 2005

Diploma, Computer Engineering (3.7 GPA)

Honors & Activities: Class Representative (Class Size: 50), Students Committee

EXPERIENCE

PRICELINE (Booking Holdings) | Toronto, ON

Senior Software Engineer

Mar 2020 - present

- Designed and developed APIs (GraphQL & REST) for Search platform for Vacation Packages on Priceline
- Developed Stream & Unary gRPC APIs using Java Rx programming improved the API performance by 30%
- Streamlined and automated release processes for CI/CD for Java apps improved build pipeline efficiency by 20%
- Test-driven Development with Unit tests and Integration tests, achieved the test coverage of 90%
- Productionalise applications and ship to On-Prem and GCP systems
- Performed code reviews and mentored Junior Engineers
- Performed Pager Duty (On Call) L1 support for all the applications that the team owns
- Analyzed Splunk and New Relic Dashboards to troubleshoot production incidents

EXPEDIA GROUP (Contract) | Bellevue, WA

Software Dev Engineer II

Jun 2019 – Feb 2020

Working on scalable data pipeline application to produce and consume data to and from Kinesis streams and process those data to and from various partners for Expedia. Responsible to design, develop, test and implement entire application from Development to all the way till production using CI/CD pipeline.

- Migrated data pipeline application from Kafka to AWS Kinesis using KPL / KCL Library, in Java and Kotlin, that decreased p90 response time by 30%
- Developed Kinesis Streams to produce and consume data to and from partners with a volume of 4000 tps
- Implemented Micrometers to record and log metrics to Graphite / Grafana
- Contributed to an in-house Opensource Project Messaging-Client Library, a messaging framework
- Test-driven Development with Unit tests and Component tests to validate business cases
- Performed load tests on REST APIs using Maven Gatling
- · Performed code reviews and mentored junior developers and interns
- Performed Pager Duty (On Call) L1 support for all the applications that the team owns
- Analyzed Splunk / Kibnana / Grafana Dashboard to troubleshoot production incidents

T-MOBILE (via ProKarma Inc.) | Bothell, WA

Software Engineer III

Jan 2019 - Jun 2019

This application is for Retail Store - to enhance its in-store mobility devices to be loaded with latest firmware that helps the sales reps to activate / sell the products to the walk-in customers.

- Developed AWS Lambda Functions in Java
- Developed Swagger Docs based on Open API Specifications
- Developed and Contributed to an in-house Opensource Project Jazz, a serverless platform
- Tracked features, stories, issues and tasks in Rally
- Test-driven Development with more than 80% coverage of Unit tests.
- · Performed code reviews across the team

GREAT WEST-LIFE (via Judge Group) | Toronto, ON

Senior Backend Developer

Mar 2018 - Dec 2018

Hired as a backend developer to work on a digital transformation project, developed by an agile team to help the insurance advisors, to enable sign up for new insurance term policies that integrates with various back-end systems. The application increased the efficiency of the application's sign-up process from 120 mins to 10 mins.

- Designed and implemented Spring boot RESTful Microservices for a customer-facing application, which enhances the customer experience
- Designed and developed application persistence using MongoDB and Redis Cache
- Developed Bamboo build and deployment plans to enable CI (Continuous Integration) Pipeline
- Developed event-driven REST APIs with Active MQs
- Developed Docker Images and Docker compose files
- Tracked features, stories, issues and tasks in JIRA
- Test-driven Development with more than 80% of Unit tests using Mockito and Spring Runner frameworks
- · Performed code reviews across the team

ROGERS COMMUNICATIONS INC (via Procom Inc) | Brampton, ON

Software Development Engineer

Jun 2016 - Feb 2018

The application serves as Enterprise Service Bus (ESB), a middleware application that integrates with various back-end applications through different semantics and protocols.

- Designed and implemented enterprise-level service layer, includes both RESTful and SOAP web-services, which serves various channels include consumer, retail, and Enterprise Business Units
- Developed synchronous and asynchronous webservices using Java, Oracle SOA Suite, JMS Queues for performance and reliability
- · Developed event-driven REST APIs with JMS Queues
- Developed PL/SQL Queries and Stored Procedures
- Analyzed Incidents and tickets on the Production Servers

VIRGIN MOBILE CANADA (via XpertVantage) | Toronto, ON

Software Development Engineer

Jun 2015 - Jun 2016

The application serves as a middleware between Virgin Mobile member facing front-end application and various back-end systems. The application carries out various self-serve functionalities to serve members for both prepaid and postpaid line of business.

- Designed and implemented RESTful web-service APIs for Virgin mobile app and web
- Developed Technical Detailed Design Documents based on the business requirements
- Developed service layers, and SOAP and RESTful web-services using Java/JEE
- Developed build scripts using ANT/WLST

TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES | Toronto, ON

IT Analyst

Sep 2008 – Jun 2015

The application serves as a middleware between Rogers IVR front-end application and various back-end systems, carries out various self-serve functionalities to serve members without involving live agents

- Developed SOAP web-services for various IVR applications, including platform replacement project, which performs self-serve operations for consumer and business channels
- Designed and developed a service to identify the callers for IVR apps, using parallel processing and coherence caching, which improved the performance by 300% and reduced the operating cost by 56%
- · Led and mentored a team of 6 individuals
- Developed Server-Monitoring utility using WebLogic Mbeans, which monitors the servers' state and thread;
 raises alert notifications, in the case of an anomaly
- Developed Socket programming to connect to the backend systems using TCP/IP in client-server architecture